A Guide to the Augusta County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1746-1912
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Augusta County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1746-1912
The Library of Virginia
Augusta County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1746-001-1912-095
Digital images.
Augusta County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in transfer of court papers from Augusta County under accession numbers 43054, 43089,43167, 43449, and 43608.
Historical Information
Chancery Causes are cases of equity. According to Black's Law Dictionary they are "administered according to fairness as contrasted with the strictly formulated rules of common law." A judge, not a jury, determines the outcome of the case.
Augusta County was named for Augusta of Saxe-Gotha, who married Frederick Louis, Prince of Wales, and was the mother of King George III. It was formed from Orange County by a statute of 1738 that stipulated that when the population was large enough the new county government would begin to function. The county court first met on 9 December 1745. The county courthouse is in Staunton, and the county administrative offices are in Verona.
Augusta County was the site of a Superior Court of Chancery that held court in Staunton from 1802 to 1832. The Superior Courts of Chancery were created by an act of the General Assembly passed on 23 January 1802. In order to expedite the hearing of chancery suits, the High Court of Chancery was abolished and the state was divided into three chancery districts with a Superior Court of Chancery for each district. For this reason these courts were sometimes called "District Courts of Chancery." Suits heard in these courts were typically cases appealed from the local courts. A transcript of the suit from the local court was commonly filed with the appeal. Litigants could by-pass the local courts and file their suits in the chancery district court directly. Of the three original Superior Courts of Chancery - Staunton, Richmond (City), and Williamsburg - only the records of the Staunton district remain.
From 1802 to 1812, the Staunton district consisted of localities found in the western half of the Commonwealth including the ones in present day West Virginia: Augusta, Bath, Berkeley, Botetourt, Brooke, Frederick, Grayson, Greenbrier, Hampshire, Hardy, Harrison, Jefferson, Kanawha, Lee, Monongalia, Monroe, Montgomery, Ohio, Pendleton, Randolph, Rockbridge, Rockingham, Russell, Shenandoah, Tazewell, Washington, Wood, and Wythe counties.
In 1812, the General Assembly created additional Superior Courts of Chancery which reduced the number of localities in the Staunton district to the following: Albemarle, Amherst, Augusta, Bath, Botetourt, Cabell, Greenbrier, Kanawha, Mason, Monroe, Nelson, Pendleton, Rockbridge, and Rockingham counties.
Scope and Content
Augusta County (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1746-1912, are indexed into the Chancery Records Index. Cases are identified by style of suit consisting of plaintiff and defendant names. Surnames of others involved in a suit, including secondary plaintiffs and defendants, witnesses, deponents and affiants, and family members with surnames different from the plaintiff or defendant are indexed. Chancery causes often involved the following: divisions of estates or land, disputes over wills, divorces, debt, and business disputes. Predominant documents found in chancery causes include bills (plaintiff's complaint), answers (defendant's response), decrees (court's decision), depositions, affidavits, correspondence, lists of heirs, deeds, wills, business records, or vital statistics, among other items. Plats, if present, are noted, as are wills from localities with an incomplete record of wills or localities other than the one being indexed.
Chancery causes are useful when researching local history, genealogical information, and land or estate divisions. They are a valuable source of local, state, social, and legal history and serve as a primary source for understanding a locality's history.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Additional Augusta County Court Records can be found on microfilm at The Library of Virginia web site. See A Guide to Virginia County and City Records on Microfilm
See the Chancery Records Index to search for chancery suits of additional Virginia localities.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Augusta County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
African Americans--History.; Business enterprises--Virginia--Augusta County.; Debt--Virginia--Augusta County.; Divorce suits--Virginia--Augusta County.; Estates (Law)--Virginia--Augusta County.; Equity--Virginia--Augusta County.; Land subdivision--Virginia--Augusta County.
Geographical Names:
Augusta County (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Chancery causes--Virginia--Augusta County.; Deeds--Virginia--Augusta County.; Judicial records--Virginia--Augusta County.; Land records--Virginia--Augusta County.; Local government records--Virginia--Augusta County.; Plats--Virginia--Augusta County.; Wills--Virginia--Augusta County.
Added Entry - Corporate Name:
Augusta County (Va.) County Court.; Augusta County (Va.) Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery.; Augusta County (Va.) Superior Court of Chancery.
Selected Suits of Interest
- 1752-006: Thomas West vs. Exr. of Benjamin Borden, etc. -
  Included in this suit is a bond of performance to Arthur Baret of Orange County for 850 acres of land and if the survey shows a problem with the 850 acres, Borden will refund some of the money Mr. Baret paid for the land. The bond is dated 23 January 1739-40. Both men were living in Orange County at the time of the bond.
- 1763-001: Jeremiah Seely vs. Joseph Carpenter etc. -
  Joseph Carpenter is Jeremiah Seely's father-in-law and had given him bonds to use to buy land near said Joseph. Because of the French and Indian War being fought in the area of Jeremiah's home, he moved his family to Maryland during the conflict. When he returned he found that Joseph had given his land to John Mann. Jeremiah sued to get the land back.
- 1768-003: William Foster vs. Exrs of James Patton -
  In John Buchanan's answer to the Bill, he states that Col. Patton was killed sometimes in the year of 1755. He had intended to take out a patent for land on the New River but got in a dispute with the Governor over a fee of a poistole for signing the patents which Patton and others refused to pay. Patton was killed by the Indians on the Frontier while he was in the service of the Government during the Indian War. Before Patton's death, the Governor hindered Patton and others from settling and getting patents on lands on the waters of the Mississippi River. The people were told to withdraw from that area.
- 1768-008: Samuel Akerling vs. Valentine Zinn etc. -
  Samuel's brother lived on the Frontier of the Colony upon the waters of the Yawyawganie. In the last war he was taken prisoner by the Indians and his house was burned. Garret Zinn had bought land from the brother. Garret took his family to North Carolina to prevent them from being murdered in the last war. He died there and Valentine Zinn is his son and heir at law.
- 1770-003: John Smith vs. Exrs. of James Patton -
  John Smith formed a company in 1741 with Zacariah Lewis, William Waller, Ben Waller, Robert Green, and James Patton to take up and survey 100,000 acres between the waters of the James River and the Roanoke River. James Patton overtime bought out the shares from the partners and got his own grant for the land. John Smith had surveyed the land and wanted payment. Patton also offered him a sixth part of Zachariah Lewis' land. This suit was an effort to settle John Smith and James Patton's business arrangements. From reading the bill, one can infer that John Smith was captured by the French and Indians in 1756 and held until 1758.
- 1786-001: Joseph Bell etc. vs. John Francis -
  William Bell's father David Bell wanted to buy land from Mr. Francis. Mr. Francis wanted to buy a slave. Mr. Bell promised to go to Maryland and buy a slave for a lower price. Unfortunately, when Mr. Bell arrived in Maryland, the price of slaves had grown and he did not purchase a slave. This suit concerns the disagreement that resulted because Mr. Bell did not buy a slave.
- 1786-002: James Hayes vs. George Berry -
  This suit concerns the purchase of a slave named Rachel who ran away and the purchase of a slave named China in her place.
- 1787-006: William Bell etc. vs. Daniel Ofriel, etc. -
  William and Samuel Bell, Daniel Ofriel and John Cunningham agreed to purchase beef and pork for the Albemarle Barracks. They encounter much difficulty, including snow, but finally bought the animals in Halifax County, NC. Lots of depositions are included in this folder.
- 1789-001: Richard Mathews vs. John Campbell -
  Richard Mathews agreed to sell John Campbell salt and deerskins. The price of salt fell and things got bad. There are business letters from 11 September 1781 through March 2, 1786 included in the folder.
- 1794-011: John Fudge vs. Benajah Thompson -
  John Fudge purchased slaves Libby and Will for Mr. Thompson. There was a disagreement over how much he had paid and how much he owed. It turned out "Libby" and "Will" were really "Kitty" and "Billy", mulatto children of Sarah Otway. The Church Wardens of Littleton Parish in Cumberland County had bound them to Benajah Thompson in August 1775. Benjamin Wilson, a Justice of the Peace, gave a statement that the two children were free persons and that they were carried out of the county by Bartlet Thompson.
- 1796-007: Alexander Stuart vs. Samuel McChesney -
  Samuel McChesney and his father-in-law Samuel Herring were involved in buying servants on consignment in 1787. This suit has copies of accounts.
- 1796-008: James Kelzo etc. vs. Samuel McChesney -
  James Kelzo, James Wilson and Samuel Chesney purchased servants together. The Bill list the name of some of the servants: Darby Hart, Martin Supple, John Haley, Pierce Jenkings, Bridget O Daniel and Elizabeth Insol. The answer names some of the people who bought the servants and Hines and Kelly, two of the servants. There is information about the servants in the accounts. One account gives the names of over 30 servants.
- 1802-018: Joseph Stover etc. vs. John Crockwell -
  There were two lotteries held to get money to build a Lutheran Church in Strasburg, Shenandoah County. The cause concerns the mistakes the people running the lotteries made.
- 1803-047: James Bayley (Bailey) vs. Andrew Moore -
  James Bailey was described in the depositions of Cornelius Dorman and James Gold as a man whose principle support came from "horses jockeying, buying, selling, swapping, and trading in other properties" and they "believe he is capable of taking any advantage in his power to accomplish without respect to Justice..." This cause concerns a gray horse that was said to be blind.
- 1803-089: James McMeechen vs Exr. of James Rumsey -
  James Rumsey according to the Bill "was versed in the Doctrines of Hydrostatics, central forces, and the Law of gravitation" and came up with an invention that was a steam boiler that could be used to cause improvement to Doctor Barkers Mill. A group of men formed a Rumseyan Society in 1784 to help pay for the experiments of Mr. Rumsey's invention. They hoped that Mr. Rumsey's invention would be able make "boats sail against rapid streams". Mr. Rumsey eventually moved to London and the suit includes letters written from London in 1789, 1791 and 1792. There is one letter dated 1788 written in Philadelphia just before he left for London. The letters talk about ship building, the building of a canal in Ireland, the situation in France and other interesting remarks.
- 1804-051: Joseph A. Smith etc. vs. George Black (alias George Schwartz) -
  There was a fight at George Black's Tavern that Mr. Black claimed resulted from Joseph A. Smith and Jacob Keller being drunk and attacking him. Mr. Black claims they broke his leg. The jury in Shenandoah County believed his account of the event. Mr. Smith and Mr. Keller have a different story about the event and they are suing in the Chancery District Court to have the County Court verdict overturned.
- 1804-068: Edward Kennedy vs. Joas Miller and Rebecca Miller -
  Joas and his daughter Rebecca obtained two judgments against Edward for getting her pregnant. Edward took the case to the High Court of Chancery to get an injunction against the judgments. Edward and his witnesses said the neighborhood men took great liberties with Rebecca and her sisters. The Millers' witnesses said Rebecca and her sisters were well behaved. There are at least 14 depositions.
- 1804-133: Thomas Grigg etc. vs. Abram Davenport etc. -
  This cause concerns the selling of the Glebe Land of the Protestant Episcopal Church in Norborne Parish (Norbourn Parish) by the Overseers of the Poor for Jefferson County (and Norbourn Parish).
- 1805-005: William Bryan vs. Lewis Bible etc. -
  William Bryan's brother Morgan was considered a lunatic. There are numerous depositions about his behavior. This cause gives information about how society dealt with people who were insane.
- 1805-041: Elizabeth Russell vs. John Doyell etc. -
  John Doyell sold Elizabeth land on 23 February 1795. She discovered that he did not own the land. He sued her to get her to pay all of her bond for the land. She sued for an injunction in 1799. She was back in court in 1803, at which time the land he sold her was surveyed and the true owners proved ownership.
- 1805-043: Rep(s) of Gen. Thomas Nelson vs. Nathaniel Burwell, trst., etc. -
  Dispute over western Virginia property owned by Gen. Thomas Nelson - signer of the Declaration of Independence, Revolutionary War hero, and governor of Virginia. Nelson's last will and testament is an exhibit in the suit.
- 1805-090: Trst(s) of Washington Academy vs. Robert Gold -
  In 1803, Washington Academy burned down. The inhabitants of Lexington wanted to rebuild the Academy in Lexington. Robert Gold sold them the land but problems arose about getting water for the academy from a spring on the other side Mr. Gold's property. There is a copy of the Rector and Trustees minutes from the meeting concerning the arrangements made for the new buildings in Lexington. There is a copy of the minutes concerning getting the water for the Academy. (Washington Academy eventually became Washington and Lee University.)
- 1806-030: George Mitchell vs. Trst(s) of William Bowyer -
  George Mitchell bought land at a trustee sale of William Bowyer's land. Jacob Kinney, the trustee would never give him a deed for the land. Mr. Mitchell searched for the land and could not find it. Mr. Mitchell concluded that there was not any land. Mr. Kinney had obtained a judgment against Mr. Mitchell and Mr. Mitchell obtained an injunction in April 1806. There is a copy of a deed, dated 29 August 1806 for the land that was used as an exhibit.
- 1806-059: Thomas Boydstone vs. Abraham Sheppard etc. -
  Thomas Boydstone purchased land from two men who had obtained Northern Neck Land Grants from Lord Fairfax. Thomas Caton had received his grant for 196 acres on 31 May 1751 and Vacheal Metcalf (Medcalfe) had received a grant for 300 acres on 7 January 1755. Mr. Boydstone bought 112 acres of the 300 acres grant. He did not have any problems about his land until 1791 when Abraham Sheppard sued to get ownership of his land. There had been a dispute between Lord Fairfax and the Crown. This cause gives a history of this dispute and other disputes over the patents and grants issued in that area of Virginia.
- 1807-006: John Crawford vs. Timothy Green etc. -
  Both parties made several surveys and entries on same land grant in state of Pennsylvania.
- 1807-015: John Craigen etc. vs. Michael Thorn etc. -
  Land dispute involves Thomas Lord Fairfax, proprietor of the Northern Neck of Virginia, settling a very valuable tract of land lying on the south branch of the Potowmack River
- 1807-036: Rep(s) of Thomas Johnson vs. Exr of James Culbertson etc. -
  Suit references the selling of valuable stud horse for 800 acres of military land.
- 1807-047: James Houston vs. John Divisure -
  The defendant visited the plaintiff and offers to cure his cancer.
- 1807-051: Thomas Mitchell etc. vs. James Barnett -
  The plaintiff sued the defendant over possession of slave Rachel and her seven offspring.
- 1807-067: Col. William Robinson vs. Col. Arthur Campbell -
  This suit was land dispute on border between Virginia and North Carolina - where there was "no established line separating the two states." The contestants disagreed on the location of the NC-VA border. References made to surveys of the border made by Joshua Fry and Peter Jefferson and Virginia and North Carolina border commissions.
- 1807-099: Agness Cunningham McCroy vs. David McCroy -
  This suit was an early divorce suit involving charges of abuse and destitution.
- 1807-116: Edmond Pendleton, surv partner vs. James Davison -
  Pendleton was a surviving partner of Virginia's Loyal Company, influential land speculators, involved in many of Augusta's counties early chancery suits.
- 1807-151: Samuel Greenlee vs. Elizabeth Moore etc. and Elizabeth Moore vs. Samuel Greenlee -
  The suit involved the possession and lease by Robert E. Lee's father, Henry "Light Horse Harry" Lee of a certain farm in Rockbridge County known as "Sidney Cove."
- 1807-152: Exrs. of Michael Fackler and Peter Heiskell vs. Corporation of Staunton -
  The suit involved the violation of local ordinance by Heiskell for not opening a ditch to convey water to the town through his lot. Fackler at the time of his death had a lease and was in possession of mills on the stream from which said water is contemplated to be taken by the corporation. One of Fackler's executors is a nearby resident and the other serves as a member of the town's Common Council.
- 1808-097: Jane Allison by, etc. vs. William Allison -
  The suit involved a plot to get rid of wife to state of Kentucky because she had become rendered helpless by severe rheumatism. Plot centers on a horse, some money and a letter sent by a mysterious individual.
- 1808-124: John Carter Littlepage vs. Admr. of John Oliver etc. -
  The suit involved a contract dispute over partnership in a public house at Hot Springs, Bath County and profits of the labor of slaves purchased by partners. Includes detailed accounts of eighteenth century business in Bath County.
- 1809-041: Margaret Bowyer, widow, etc, Margaret Lewis and Anthony Mustoe etc. vs. William Bowyer and Margaret Lewis -
  The suit includes a plat of the town of Warm Springs in Bath County.
- 1809-078: James McKerrey vs. Fontaine Maury etc. -
  The defendant in the suit served as mayor of Fredericksburg during the 1790s and early 1800s. At this time, he is now a merchant that apparently owes the plaintiff a quantity of butter and cheese.
- 1809-084: William Little vs. Thomas Flagg -
  The suit involves the establishment of a public road - contains plats and petitions. The answer of one of the defendants sums up the history of the case.
- 1809-088: Richard Price etc. vs. Peter Randolph -
  The suit involves a mulatto petitioning for his freedom. He assumed another person's identity. The defendant was the grandson to Lewis Randolph.
- 1809-095: John Hook vs. Nanny Pege etc. -
  John Hook of Franklin County appealed suit from Montgomery County Court to the Superior Court of Chancery in Staunton to deny Nanny Pege (or Nanny Pagee) and her children their freedom. See also Nanny Pegee et cetera versus John Hook and Zachariah Stanley, 1808 Apr. heard in Franklin County (Va.) District Court where the suit began and ended.
- 1809-158: William Ward vs. Rachael Skidmore -
  A dispute over a supposed breach of marriage contract.
- 1810-031: James Maxwell vs. Thomas Pickens etc. -
  A dispute between Maxwell and Col. William Ingles over property rights in Tazewell County. In his bill of complaint. Maxwell references the death of his daughters that took place 20 years earlier during an attack by Native Americans.
- 1810-076: George Poage etc. vs. James Brown etc. -
  The suit involves settlement on the Ohio River in the state of Kentucky.
- 1810-088: Fanny Harlow by etc. vs. Nathaniel Harlow -
  The suit involves a divorce by extreme cruelty. Husband has considerable wealth and court is last resort for plaintiff who after 40 years of marriage has nothing.
- 1810-138: William Lewis vs. Archibald Wood and Archibald Wood vs. William Lewis -
  The suit involves thousands of acres of military land in Kentucky.
- 1810-148: William McClung, Sr. vs. Andrew Moore -
  Andrew Moore was a member of Congress and VA State senator from 1804-1809. The suit involves disputed tracts of land in present day Greenbrier County, West Virginia.
- 1810-154: Joseph Watson, the younger vs. Elizabeth Longacre etc. -
  The suit involves contesting a will and land in Shenandoah County.
- 1811-008: Robert Lewright v. Rep(s) of John Hite -
  Combined with other suits to be heard at the same time, The suit includes the will of John Hite of Berkeley County which bequeathed land in the Western District of Augusta County. The will mentions land Hite acquired from Cherokee Indians.
- 1811-018: William McClanahan etc. vs. Patterson Hannah -
  The suit involves the purchase of land on the Roanoke River in what became Botetourt County in 1757 by Erwin Patterson of New Castle, Delaware. The family then moved on to Kentucky.
- 1811-031: Andrew Moore vs. John Stuart etc. -
  The suit contains letters, dated 1795, concerning surveying of western lands; one letter from Greenbrier County.
- 1811-036: James Moseley vs. James McMurran etc. -
  Concerns business interests and trade with France, through Alexandria. Depositions from Oswego, New York, Alexandria, Hampshire County.
- 1811-049: Daniel Norcutt vs. Admr. of George Dillard -
  Contract dispute over terms of an agreement to hire two enslaved men to carry produce and other articles from Lynchburg and other places along the James River to Richmond.
- 1812-006: John Bollar, Sr. vs. William McClintie alias McClintock -
  Case contains multiple depositions about alleged mistreatment of an enslaved woman.
- 1812-017: Jane Beverley vs. John H. Hyde etc. -
  Case concerns a 5,000-acre estate in Botetourt containing "valuable ore banks" and iron works.
- 1812-042: William McMechen and James P. Heath vs. John H. Hyde etc. -
  Suit relates to a dispute over the ownership of slaves in Rockbridge County. A bill of sale for 31 of the slaves is an exhibit in the suit. It list the names of the slaves, family relationships (husband, wife, children), occupations and the appraised monetary value of each of the 31 slaves.
- 1812-059: Andrew Anderson vs. John Fulk -
  Plaintiff is a free man of color suing to keep his land.
- 1813-054: Thomas Stuart vs. Heirs of John Duncan -
  Suit concerns dispute over a marriage contract, which is included in the case.
- 1813-069: Heirs of William Boon, Sr., vs. Joseph Gatewood, etc. -
  Case includes a copy of a 1754 proclamation from Governor Dinwiddie to encourage men to enlist in defense of the colony and help build a fort on the river Ohio "to oppose any further encroachments or hostile attempts of the French and the Indians in their interest."
- 1813-085: James Logan vs. Molly~, etc. -